The early summer days on a farm are the happiest and fairest days of the year.
Lilacs bloom and make the air sweet and then fade.
Apple blossoms come with the lilacs and the bees visit around among the apple
trees. The days grow warm and soft.
School ends and children have time to play and to fish for trouts in the
brook. Avery often brought a trout home in his pocket, warm and stiff and ready
to be fried for supper.
Now that school was over, Fern visited the barn almost every day to sit quietly
on her stool. The animals treated her as an equal. The sheep lay calmly at her feet.
Around the 1st of July, the workh horses were hitched to the mowing machine, and
Mr. Zuckerman climbed into the seat and drove into the field. All morning you
could hear the rattle of the machine as it went round and round while the tall
grass fell down behind the cutter bar in long green swaths.
Next day, if there was no thunderher, all hands would help rake and pitch and
load, and the hay would be hauled to the barn in the high hay wagon, with Fern
and Avery riding at the top of the load.
Then the hay would be hoisted, sweet and warm, into the big loft, until the whole
barn seemed like a wonderful bed of Timothy and Clover. It was fine to jump
in and perfect to hide in. And sometimes Avery would find a little grass snake in
the hay and would add it to the other things in his pocket.
Early summer days are a jubilee time for birds. In the fields, around the house,
in the barn, in the woods, in the swamp, everywhere love and songs and nests and
eggs. From the edge of the woods, the white-throatated sparrow, which must
come all the way from Boston, calls, "Oh, Peabody, Peabody, Peabody."
On an apple bow, the Phoebe teeters and wags its tail and says, "Pee, Phoebe."
The song Sparrow, who knows how brief and lovely life is, says, "Sweet, sweet,
sweet interlude. Sweet, sweet, sweet interlude."
If you enter the barn, the swallows swoop down from their nests and scold.
"Cheeky cheeky," they say.
In early summer, there are plenty of things for a child to eat and drink and
suck and chew. Dandelion stems are full of milk. Clover heads are loaded with
nectar. The frigid air is full of ice cold drinks. Everywhere you look, is
life. Even the little ball of spit on the weed stalk, if you poke it apart,
has a green worm inside it. And on the underside of the leaf of the potato vine
are the bright orange eggs of the potato bug. It was on a day in early summer
that the goose eggs hatched. This was an important event in the barn cellar. Fern
was there sitting on her stool when it happened.
Except for the goose herself, Charlotte was the first to know that the gosslings
had at last arrived. The goose knew a day in advance that they were coming.
She could hear their weak voices calling from inside the egg. She knew that they
were in a desperately cramped position inside the shell and were most anxious
to break through and get out, so she sat quite still and talked less than usual.
When the first goling poked its gray green head through the goose's feathers
and looked around, Charlotte spied it and made the announcement.
"I am sure," she said, "that every one of us here will be gratified to learn
that after 4 weeks of unremitting effort and patience on the part of our friend
the goose, she now has something to show for it. The glings have arrived. May I
offer my sincere congratulations?
Oh, thank you, thank you, thank you, said the goose, nodding and bowing
shamelessly. Thank you, said the gender.
Congratulations, shouted Wilbur. How many golings are there? I can only see one. There are
seven, said the goose.
Fine, said Charlotte. Seven is a lucky number. Luck had nothing to do with
this, said the goose. It was good management and hard work.
At this point, Templeton showed his nose from his hiding place under Wilbur's
trough. He glanced at Fern, then crept cautiously toward the goose, keeping
close to the wall. Everyone watched him, for he was not well-liked, not trusted.
Look, he began in his sharp voice. You say you have uh seven glings. There were
eight eggs. What happened to the other egg? Uh why didn't it hatch? It's a dud,
I guess, said the goose. What are you going to do with it? Uh," continued
Templeton, his little round beady eyes fixed on the goose.
"You can have it," replied the goose.
"Roll it away and add it to that nasty collection of yours." Templeton had a
habit of picking up unusual objects around the farm and storing them in his
home. He saved everything.
Certainly, certainly, said the gander.
You may have the egg, but I'll tell you one thing, Timon. If I ever catch you
poking, oaking, oaking your ugly nose around our glings, I'll give you the worst pounding a rat
ever took. And the gander opened his strong wings and beat the air with them
to show his power.
He was strong and brave, but the truth is both the goose and the gander were
worried about Templeton, and with good reason.
The rat had no morals, no conscience, no scruples, no consideration, no decency,
no milk of rodent kindness, no compunctions, no higher feeling, no
friendliness, no anything. He would kill a glinging if he could get away with it.
The goose knew that. Everybody knew it.
With her broad bill, the goose pushed the unhatched egg out of the nest, and
the entire company watched in disgust while the rat rolled it away. Even
Wilbur, who could eat almost anything, was appalled. "Imagine wanting a chunky
old rotten egg," he muttered.
"A rat is a rat," said Charlotte. She laughed a tinkling little laugh. But my friends, if that
ancient egg ever breaks, this barn will be untenable.
What's that mean? asked Wilbur. It means nobody will be able to live here on
account of the smell. A rotten egg is a regular stink bomb. I won't break it,
snarled Templeton. I know what I'm doing. I handle stuff like this all the
time. He disappeared into his tunnel, pushing the goose egg in front of him.
He pushed and nudged till he succeeded in rolling it to his layer under the trough.
That afternoon, when the wind had died down, and the barnyard was quiet and
warm, the gray goose led her seven gosslings off the nest and out into the
world. Mr. Zuckerman spied them when he came with Wilbur's supper. Well, hello
there," he said, smiling all over. Let's see. One, two, three, four, five, six,
seven. Seven baby geese. Now, isn't that lovely?
Chapter 7.
Bad news.